Fraga and Peña Collection of the Ocampo Family, [1890s]-1979 (bulk 1930-1979 ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
Fraga and Peña Collection of the Ocampo Family
1890s-1979
1930-1979
C0783
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
1 linear feet 3 boxes
Ocampo, Victoria, 1890-1979.
Author Victoria Ocampo (1890-1979) was founder (1931) and editor of the magazine SUR, an important literary magazine published in Buenos Aires. The collection consists primarily of Ocampo family correspondence, particularly that of the sisters Victoria and Angelica Ocampo.
Author Victoria Ocampo (1890-1979) was founder (1931) and editor of the magazine SUR, an important literary magazine published in Buenos Aires.
Consists primarily of Ocampo family correspondence, particularly that of the sisters Victoria and Angelica Ocampo, collected by Maria Rebeca Pena and Rebeca Fraga of Argentina. Victoria Ocampo's correspondence, in Spanish and French, spans the period 1926-1978 and includes many of her impressions of writers and artists which she wrote about, such as Aldous Huxley, Graham Greene, Sergei Eisenstein and Jean Cocteau. Her correspondence is particularly strong for the many periods of time when she resided in Paris, France, and for the year 1975, when she lived in New York City and met and visited with many intellectuals. In addition, there are a few manuscripts by Victoria Ocampo, including an autobiographical memoir which the author translated from French to Spanish and sent to the Argentine writer Jose "Pepe" Bianco.
The majority of the correspondence in the collection is that of Angelica Ocampo, sister of Victoria and Silvina who, while not a writer herself, was supportive of the efforts of her two sisters to write and publish. Her correspondence includes one folder of letters by Silvina Ocampo (1903-1993), as well as letters from other friends and relatives.
There is one folder of miscellaneous correspondence to Victoria Ocampo from various authors who include the writers Andre Malraux, Mario Vargas Llosa, and Anita Loos. There are also a few reviews of the English edition of Victoria Ocampo's biography of T. E. Lawrence, 338171 T. E. (1963); letters (1930s-1970s) by Daniel Bolten, a Dutch art specialist, to Angelica Ocampo; correspondence (1900-1903) between Manuel S. Ocampo (father of Angelica, Silvina, and Victoria) and Francesco Bovio, Federico Ravina and others; and a few photographs. The Papers of Others series is small in size, but includes autograph drafts of an essay "Patagonie" ("Patagonia") by the French writer Roger Caillois.
Collection is open for research use.
Inherited by Maria Rebeca Pena from Angelica Ocampo. Sold to Princeton in 1995.
Ocampo family.; Fraga, Rebeca,compiler.; Ocampo, Angelica, d.1983.; Ocampo, Manuel S.; Ocampo, Silvina.; Pena, Maria Rebeca, compiler.; Argentine literature -- 20th century.; European literature -- 20th century.; Latin American literature -- 20th century.; Novelists, Argentine -- 20th century -- Correspondence.; Short stories, Argentine -- 20th century.; Women authors, Argentine -- 20th century -- Correspondence.; Women poets, Argentine -- 20th century -- Correspondence.; Argentina -- Intellectual life -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Family papers; Manuscripts.; Photographs.; Latin American literature
- Series 1: Angélica Ocampo (1891-1980) Papers, 1920-1979; portions of 3 boxes
  - Subseries 1A: Correspondence, 1920-1979; portions of 3 boxes
    - Anderson, Valborg “Val”, 1979; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - [Atucha], Tota, undated; 1948; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bianco, José “Pepe”, 1938; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bioy Casares, Adolfo, 1970; portion of 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bolten, Daniel “Daan”: Letters to Angélica Ocampo, 1938-1946; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bolten, Daniel “Daan”: Letters to Angélica Ocampo, 1947-1979; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - [Cosío Villegas], Daniel, 1948; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Cottier, Yvette [first wife of Roger Caillois], 1975; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - C[uesta], Eugenio, 1969-1979; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - [Dorado], Josefina, 1930s; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Embassy of France (Buenos Aires, Argentina), 1979; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Embassy of India (Buenos Aires, Argentina), 1979; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Figueroa Alenta, Luis, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Kent, Victoria, and Louise Crane(?), 1970s; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Lawrence, [Arnold W.](?), undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Llorens, Pedro, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Macarow, Vera, 1967-1975; portion of 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 16A)
    - Maeztu, Maria de, 1935; portion of 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 16B)
    - Magrini, C, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Molloy, Sylvia, 1979; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - La Nación (Buenos Aires, Argentina), 1979; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Ocampo, Miguel, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Ocampo, Pancha (Francisa Ocampo de García Victorica), 1947-1961; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Ocampo, Ramona Aguirre de (mother), 1928; portion of 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 21A)
    - Ocampo, Rosa, 1938; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Ocampo, Silvina, circa 1938-1941; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Ocampo, Silvina, 1943-1960; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Ocampo, Silvina (and A. Bioy Casares and “Marta”), 1970s; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Ocampo, Victoria: Letters to Angélica Ocampo and their parents, 1920s-1933; portion of 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Ocampo, Victoria: Letters to Angélica and Pancha Ocampo, “Tata,” and others, 1940s; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Ocampo, Victoria: Letters to Angélica and Pancha Ocampo, Pepe Bianco, and others, 1950s-1960; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Ocampo, Victoria: Letters to Angélica and Pancha Ocampo, Fryda Schultz de Mantovani, and others, 1962; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Ocampo, Victoria: Letters to Angélica and Pancha Ocampo, Fryda Schultz de Mantovani, and others, 1963; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Ocampo, Victoria: Letters to Angélica and Pancha Ocampo, 1964; 1966; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Ocampo, Victoria: Letters to Angélica Ocampo, Fryda Fryda Schultz de Mantovani, and others, 1972-1973; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Ocampo, Victoria: Letters to Angélica Ocampo, Fryda Schultz de Mantovani, and others, 1975; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Ocampo, Victoria: Two letters to Angélica Ocampo, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Oliver, María Rosa, 1924; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Ortega y Gasset Ortega, Soledad (See also Box 2, Fol.1), 1929; 1979; portion of 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Perse, Saint-John (Alexis Saint-Léger Léger) and his wife Dorothy M, 1960-1963; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Pezzoni, Enrique, 1979; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Raring, Federico “Fedi”: Letters to Josefina [Dorado] via Angélica Ocampo, 1937-1939; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Schultz de Mantovani, Fryda, 1975; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Sieyes(?), Carmina, 1967-1979; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Various Authors: Letters by Angélica Ocampo (to “Lola” “Pepin”), undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 13A)
    - Various Authors: Letters to Angélica Ocampo, 1938-1978; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Various Authors: Letters to Angélica and Silvina Ocampo (on the death of Victoria Ocampo), 1979; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Various Authors: Cards and telegrams sent to the Ocampo family on the death of Victoria Ocampo, 1979; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Ocampo, Angélica: Miscellaneous envelopes, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 1A)
  - Subseries 1B: Documents, 1931-1975; portion of 2 folders
    - Passport: Argentina, 1931-1934; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Legal document (in French) about an automobile accident, 1939; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Receipts, 1955-1975; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series 2: Victoria Ocampo (1890-1979) Papers, 1910-1979; 11 folders (2 partial)
  - Subseries 2A: Writings, 1930-1975; portion of 2 folders
    - Original manuscripts (in French Spanish) 12 AMss TMss, 1930s; 1950s; 1960; 1975; undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Reviews of her book 338171 T. E. (Lawrence of Arabia), 1963; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 2B: Correspondence, 1910-1979; portion of 7 folders
    - Canal Feijóo, Bernardo, undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Edward VIII, King (later the Duke of Windsor), 1931; 1936; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Fondane, Benjamin, 1929; 1934; undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Loos, Anita, 1963; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Martínez, Juli´n: Letter to “Benjamin”, 1910s; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Ocampo, Silvina: Letter to Victoria Ocampo, 1977; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Various Authors: Letters to Victoria Ocampo, A-Z, 1921-1979; portion of 1 folder
      - Abrams, Al, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Benavente, Jacinto, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Caillois, Roger, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Carrara, Enrico, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Ede, Jim, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Groussac, Paul, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Guasto, Padre, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Huxley, Aldous, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Huxley, Julian, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Lancelotti, Mario A., undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Malraux, Alain (stepson of André Malraux), undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Moltedo, V. F. B. de, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Moreno, Marguerite, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Ocampo, Pancha, Baeza, Pepe y Enrique, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Pezzoni, Enrique, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Rigaud, Jacques, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - San Martin, Juan C., undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Sarraute, Nathalie, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Valmorin, Louise de, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Vargas Llosa, Mario, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - unidentified (2), undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 2C: Documents, 1951-1968; 1 folder
    - Receipts, 1951; 1968; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 2D: Printed Material Memorabilia, 1950-1979; 1 folder
    - Clippings of an article by Victoria Ocampo, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Articles, invitations, programs, etc. saved by Ocampo, 1950s-1979; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Obituaries of Ocampo published in Convicción [Buenos Aires], 1979; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Printed calling cards (2) of Ocampo, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Series 3: Ocampo Family Papers, 1890-1979; 7 folders (2 partial)
  - Subseries 3A: Photographs, 1890-1979; portion of 5 folders
    - Ocampo, Angélica (1), undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Ocampo, Silvina (5), circa 1908-1920; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 15A)
    - Ocampo, Victoria (10), 1928-1979; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 15B)
    - Ocampo residences (5), circa 1963; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 15C)
    - Miscellaneous and unidentified (12), 1890s; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 15D)
  - Subseries 3B: Miscellaneous Correspondence and Documents, 1900-1979; portion of 2 folders
    - Ocampo family: miscellaneous correspondence, 1950s-1979; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Family recipes, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Legal document pertaining to the “Terreno del Bajo en San Isidro”, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Ocampo, Manuel S. (father of Victoria, Angélica, Silvina): correspondence with Francisco Bovio, Federico Ravina, and others, 1900-1903; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Series 4: Papers of Others, 1903-1979; portions of 3 boxes
  - Caillois, Roger: Autograph manuscripts, including two drafts of essay “Patagonie,” one dated 1942, 11 pp., 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Corbett: H. A.: Typescript manuscript, “A Critic in Action,” and printed article by B. H. Liddell Hart, both in English, about T. E. Lawrence, undated; 1963; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Fondane, Benjamin: Typescript manuscript about his unpublished manuscript, “Sur les rives de l'Ilyssus”, 1939; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Mendez, Jesús: Correspondence with José Bianco, 1979; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Fraga, Rebeca: Correspondence, 1973; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Angélica Ocampo Correspondence, 1929-1975; portions of 3 boxes
    - Bioy Casares, Adolfo, 1970 August 26; portion of 1 folder
      - 1 ACS to AO, 1970 August 26; portion of 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - “Lola”, 1930 August; portion of 1 folder
      - 2 ALsS by AO, (July), undated; circa 1930 August; portion of 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 13A)
    - Macarow, Vera, 1975; portion of 1 folder
      - 1 ALS to AO, 1975; portion of 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 16A)
    - Maeztu, Maria de [sister of Ramiro de Maeztu], 1935; portion of 1 folder
      - 1 ALS to AO, 1935; portion of 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 16B)
    - Ocampo, Victoria, 1929; portions of 2 boxes
      - 1 ALS to AO, 1929; portion of 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - 1 ACS (re A. Huxley) to AO, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Ortega y Gasset, José, 1929; portion of 1 folder
      - 2 ALsS to AO, 1929; portion of 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - “Pepin”, 1930; portion of 1 folder
      - 1 ALS by AO, circa 1930; portion of 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 13A)
    - 2 envelopes addressed to AO, no letters, 1933; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 1A)
    - Passport of AO, Argentina, 1931-1934; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Victoria Ocampo Papers, 1921-1977; 2 folders (2 partial)
    - Benavente, Jacinto, 1929; portion of 1 folder
      - 2 ALsS, 1 ACS to VO, 1929; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Caillois, Roger, 1971; portion of 1 folder
      - 1 ALS to VO, 1971; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Groussac, Paul, 1921-1926; portion of 1 folder
      - 2 ALsS to VO, 1921; 1926; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Huxley, Aldous, 1959; portion of 1 folder
      - 1 ALS to VO, 1959; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Huxley, Julian, 1968; portion of 1 folder
      - 1 ALS to VO, 1968; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Moreno, Marguerite, 1946; portion of 1 folder
      - 1 ALS to VO, 1946; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Ocampo, Pancha, Baeza, Pepe y Enrique, 1951; portion of 1 folder
      - 1 TL by VO, 1951; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Sarraute, Nathalie, 1966; portion of 1 folder
      - 1 ALS to VO, 1966; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Valmorin, Louise de, 1977; portion of 1 folder
      - 1 ALS to VO, 1977; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Manuscript: “Llegué por primera vez a Mar del Plata...” (Un articulo [speech?] escritas a m´quina de VO sobre el Mar de Plata de su infancia.), TMsS, 4 pp., 2nd revision, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript: “Sarmiento” (Resumen de un argumento de VO sobre una pelicula que transcurre en la época de Sarmiento Protagonistas: Enrique Ocampo y Felicitas Guerrero.), TMs, 7 pp., 2nd revision, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1903-1928; portions of 2 boxes (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Ocampo, Manuel S., 1903; portion of 1 folder
      - 1 ALS by Bovio Amilcare to MSO, 1903; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Ocampo, Ramona Aguirre de, 1928; portion of 1 folder
      - 1 ALS to “Mis queridas hijas” [daughters], 1928; portion of 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 21A)
    - Ocampo, Silvina, 1908; portion of 1 folder
      - 1 photograph, circa 1908; portion of 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 15A)